<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-03-21T16:52:47+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Language and Linguistics | Natural Language Processing | Leadership </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Language Technologies FOR ALL</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/LT4All/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Language Technologies FOR ALL"/><published>2025-03-05T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-05T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/LT4All</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/LT4All/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eric-m-jackson_imagine-for-a-moment-waking-up-one-morning-activity-7303082319005827073-f0Mm">See this post on LinkedIn</a></p> <p>Imagine for a moment, waking up one morning to discover that your language could not be used on any of your devices. Your phone and tablet do not display your language. None of your devices allow you to type in your language. If you have a smart speaker, it no longer responds to your language. At best, you can record and send an audio message in your communications app of choice (whose interface is no longer in your own language), but the automatic transcription feature no longer works for your language. This was the question posed by one of the speakers at <a href="https://www.lt4all2025.eu/">the UNESCO Language Technologies for All Conference</a> that I attended last week. Sit with this for a moment and reflect on what that would feel like.</p> <p>Although digital devices work just fine for a few hundred of the world’s most populous languages, the situation this speaker asked us to imagine is the daily experience for more than a billion people, who speak one of the thousands of languages for which digital tools—even “simple” tools like keyboards, dictionaries, and spell checkers, not to mention more complex tools like large language models or automated speech recognition systems—do not yet exist.</p> <p>To be sure, for many of these people, digital devices and even access to the Internet are likely unavailable, as well. However, <strong>if our goal is to bring the positive benefits of digital platforms and communication tools to all people, then making those tools function in the languages that those people prefer is an important part of that task.</strong></p> <p>This is a complex problem. One part of the solution involves assembling corpora of digital data in these languages. This is not an easy task, and it raises questions like, <em>who should have the right to manage this kind of language data?</em> Some language communities have taken intentional action to change the trajectory of their language’s digital footprint. At this conference, the <a href="https://naijavoices.com/">NaijaVoices</a> project introduced their concept of “data farming” (an intentional contrast with “data mining”) for languages of Nigeria as an example of a community-based solution to this problem.</p> <p>The trajectory of a language’s digital footprint is also related to issues of language preservation and revitalization. At this conference, we also heard examples of the successful work that has been done by the <a href="https://estonianworld.com/technology/estonias-ai-gamble-can-four-billion-words-secure-its-languages-future/">Estonian</a> and <a href="https://www.prospect-journal.org/articles/blog-post-title-two-yjhc2-rftfm-7lsm8">Icelandic</a> language communities, to develop language technologies that aim to promote the use of these languages in digital contexts.</p> <p>There remains much work to be done, but I’m excited to be among those who are working for equitable approaches that promote the well-being of communities, regardless of the languages that they prefer to use!</p> <div style="position:absolute; width:100%; height:100%;"> <a href="https://www.lt4all2025.eu/" target="_blank"><img src="/assets/img/20250305-1.jpg" style="vertical-align:middle; text-align:center"/> </a> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AILT"/><category term="LinkedIn"/><category term="HLT"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What if you woke up one morning, and your language could not be used on any of your devices?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Celebrating International Mother Language Day</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/International_Mother_Language_Day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Celebrating International Mother Language Day"/><published>2025-02-18T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-18T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/International_Mother_Language_Day</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/International_Mother_Language_Day/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eric-m-jackson_international-mother-language-day-united-activity-7297682735412690944-GNj5">See this post on LinkedIn</a></p> <p>This February 21st marks the 25th anniversary of the establishment of <a href="https://www.un.org/en/observances/mother-language-day">International Mother Language Day</a>. This is a good time to be reminded of what this celebration represents.</p> <p><a href="https://docs.un.org/en/A/RES/61/266">The original UN resolution</a> establishing International Mother Language Day highlights several points about language:</p> <ul> <li><strong>multilingualism</strong>—when one person speaks more than one language—is a means of promoting, protecting and preserving diversity of languages and cultures globally</li> <li>genuine multilingualism promotes unity in diversity and promotes international understanding, both of which contribute to peaceful and mutually beneficial international relationships</li> </ul> <p>Since this is a UN resolution, it’s natural that it focuses on issues at an international scale. However, issues of language and multilingualism can be found at any level of society, from the international scale, to your town, and to your own neighborhood and schools. There are people in the places where you shop, the places where you or your children study, or even the places where you worship, who speak languages that are different from yours. That should not represent a barrier to be overcome, but an opportunity for you to learn from a different way to look at the world.</p> <p>Next week, I’ll be attending <a href="https://www.lt4all2025.eu/">the UNESCO Language Technologies for All Conference</a>. Even though multilingualism can “[foster] social development by promoting inclusion, preserving cultural heritage, and empowering language communities,” language communities differ in the language technologies that are available to them, and this results in differences in how easy it is for communities to reach their goals for their members. As part of the <a href="https://ailt.arizona.edu">Advancing Indigenous Language Technologies working group</a>, I’d like to see access to appropriate language technology tools grow for <em>all</em> of the roughly 7000 languages in the world today, not just the 50 or 100 that happen to have the most data online.</p> <p>Is there something that you could do to celebrate International Mother Language Day this year? Consider starting by simply finding out about the other languages that are spoken where you live. Tucson is the traditional home to communities who speak Hiaki and O’odham, and many other languages can now be found around town. Taking the next step and trying to <strong>learn</strong> one of these languages, to paraphrase Humphrey Bogart, could be the beginning of some beautiful friendships.</p> <div style="position:absolute; width:100%; height:100%;"> <a href="https://www.un.org/en/observances/mother-language-day" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.un.org/sites/un2.un.org/files/2020/01/mother-language-poster.jpg" style="vertical-align:middle; text-align:center"/> </a> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AILT"/><category term="LinkedIn"/><category term="HLT"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There's value in celebrating all languages]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Maintaining our values</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Keep_to_our_values/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Maintaining our values"/><published>2025-02-12T09:16:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-12T09:16:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Keep_to_our_values</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Keep_to_our_values/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eric-m-jackson_dei-nsa-dei-activity-7295475385578704896-OwTL">See this post on LinkedIn</a></p> <p>We need to make sure that the current push to get rid of DEI in government is not simply a stealthy way to reintroduce bias, echo chambers, and other things that will hinder us. Whether the recent infamous photo of a wall being repainted at the FBI academy was really at the FBI academy or not <a href="https://www.snopes.com/news/2025/02/07/fbi-core-values-mural/">https://www.snopes.com/news/2025/02/07/fbi-core-values-mural/</a>, we need to maintain the values that we hold as a country, regardless of the winds of administrative change. Those values include diversity, equity, and inclusion, as well as compassion, fairness, integrity, respect, and stability.</p> <p>Dr. Renée Burton makes the case well in this post.</p> <blockquote> <p>“Being insecure about common sense words like: diversity. equity. inclusion. will destroy not aid our economy.”</p> </blockquote> <iframe src="https://www.linkedin.com/embed/feed/update/urn:li:share:7291958128059854849" height="1598" width="504" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" title="Embedded post"> </iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="LinkedIn"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Let's maintain the values that have served us well]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MSHLT Student Laura Montenegro</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Laura_Montenegro/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MSHLT Student Laura Montenegro"/><published>2025-01-27T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-27T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Laura_Montenegro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Laura_Montenegro/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://example.com">See this post on LinkedIn</a></p> <p>Our <em>Master’s in Human Language Technology</em> program had one other student graduate in the fall semester: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/laura-montenegro-872930b2/">Laura Montenegro</a>. For her internship with <a href="https://www.cobaltspeech.com/">Cobalt Speech</a>, Laura evaluated a hybrid ASR model (using a Hidden Markov Model-Deep Neural Network) for <a href="https://medium.com/neuralspace/low-resource-language-what-does-it-mean-d067ec85dea5">low-resource languages</a> using Cobalt’s existing tools.</p> <blockquote> <p>Although “low-resource language” is the standard term to refer to languages without large existing datasets, I find the term “data-scarce language” to be less prone to misunderstanding; the “resource” that is low is <em>prepared datasets</em>, not necessarily money or people.</p> </blockquote> <p>By definition, it’s hard to find datasets for languages that are considered “low-resource,” but Laura found a workable amount of audio data for the Ewe language <a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/worldboss/ewe_bible_v2_tts">on HuggingFace</a>—great practical experience for future work in NLP and speech technology!</p> <p>Wishing you all the best in your future endeavors, Laura!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/20250127-1.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/20250127-1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="MSHLT"/><category term="students"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing MSHLT student Laura Montenegro]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MSHLT Student Charlie Accurso</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Charlie_Accurso/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MSHLT Student Charlie Accurso"/><published>2025-01-17T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-17T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Charlie_Accurso</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Charlie_Accurso/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eric-m-jackson_although-most-of-the-students-in-our-%F0%9D%98%94%F0%9D%98%A2-activity-7286053758436851712-Fiy4?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop">See this post on LinkedIn</a></p> <p>Although most of the students in our <em>Master’s in Human Language Technology</em> program graduate in the spring semester, there are a few who graduate in the fall. One of those who completed the program just a few weeks ago is <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/charlieaccurso/">Charlie Accurso</a>. For his internship, Charlie worked as a Language and AI Engineering intern on call center software, using skills in multiple languages. Because his work will be applied by his host company in an actual project, we can’t publicly share more than this!</p> <p>It’s one goal of our program that practical experience like this prepares students to make significant contributions to their workplace as soon as they finish the program. We wish you all the best in your future endeavors, Charlie!</p> <p>Check out Charlie’s public projects on his GitHub page:</p> <p><a href="https://github.com/charlieaccurso">https://github.com/charlieaccurso</a></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/20250117-1.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/20250117-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="MSHLT"/><category term="students"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing MSHLT student Charlie Accurso]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MSHLT Student Ashwin Raj</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Ashwin_Raj/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MSHLT Student Ashwin Raj"/><published>2025-01-06T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-06T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Ashwin_Raj</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Ashwin_Raj/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eric-m-jackson_with-each-new-academic-year-its-inspiring-activity-7282082146414931969-M_56?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop">See this post on LinkedIn</a></p> <p>With each new academic year, it’s inspiring to read about the projects that the students in our <em>Master’s in Human Language Technology</em> program pursue for their internship. I recently read through the portfolio for <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ashwin-raj-056140181/">Ashwin Raj</a>, who developed an Invention Classification and Market Research Tool for <a href="https://techlaunch.arizona.edu/">TECH Launch Arizona</a>. It’ll be a fortunate company that hires Ashwin when he completes his degree program this spring. I’m optimistic that he can find a role that aligns with his desire to make a positive impact in the world!</p> <p>Check out this and Ashwin’s other projects on his portfolio site:</p> <p><a href="https://ashwinr136.github.io/HLT-Internship/portfolio.html">https://ashwinr136.github.io/HLT-Internship/portfolio.html</a></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/20250106-1.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/20250106-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="MSHLT"/><category term="students"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing MSHLT student Ashwin Raj]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Who and What comprise AI Skepticism? | Eric Jackson</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/who-and-what-comprise-ai-skepticism-eric-jackson/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who and What comprise AI Skepticism? | Eric Jackson"/><published>2024-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/who-and-what-comprise-ai-skepticism--eric-jackson</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/who-and-what-comprise-ai-skepticism-eric-jackson/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A re-post of a re-post? Yes, I&#39;m sorry, but I&#39;m going to do it anyway because I found this essay helpful (and found it because of Gary Marcus). I like the way…]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vector Databases Are the Wrong Abstraction | Eric Jackson</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/vector-databases-are-the-wrong-abstraction-eric-jackson/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vector Databases Are the Wrong Abstraction | Eric Jackson"/><published>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/vector-databases-are-the-wrong-abstraction--eric-jackson</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/vector-databases-are-the-wrong-abstraction-eric-jackson/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This morning, I had just finished preparing a video+code module that introduces Retrieval-Augmented Generation systems to students in my grad-level…]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Your data enables insights. Your data drives decision-making… | Eric Jackson</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/your-data-enables-insights-your-data-drives-decision-making-eric-jackson/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your data enables insights. Your data drives decision-making… | Eric Jackson"/><published>2024-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/your-data-enables-insights-your-data-drives-decision-making--eric-jackson</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/your-data-enables-insights-your-data-drives-decision-making-eric-jackson/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Your data enables insights. Your data drives decision-making. Understanding your data brings benefits, to you and your organization. 𝗪𝗵𝗮𝘁 𝗶𝗳 𝘆𝗼𝘂𝗿…]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MSHLT Student Matthew McLaughlin</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/Matthew_McLaughlin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MSHLT Student Matthew McLaughlin"/><published>2024-08-02T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-02T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/Matthew_McLaughlin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/Matthew_McLaughlin/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eric-m-jackson_another-recent-graduate-of-the-%F0%9D%91%80%F0%9D%91%8E%F0%9D%91%A0%F0%9D%91%A1%F0%9D%91%92-activity-7225255254525722624-rlcg/">See this post on LinkedIn</a></p> <p>Another recent graduate of the <em>Master’s in Human Language Technology</em> program, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/matthew-mclaughlin-543622102/">Matthew McLaughlin</a> worked on several information extraction tasks for his internship at <a href="https://lum.ai">Lum AI</a>, a company that includes faculty from the University of Arizona and a number of MSHLT alumni. Congratulations, Matthew!</p> <p>Check out his projects on his portfolio site:</p> <p>https://mc-wut.github.io/</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/20240802-1.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/20240802-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="MSHLT"/><category term="students"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing MSHLT student Matthew McLaughlin]]></summary></entry></feed>