<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-10T17:53:54+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Language and Linguistics | Natural Language Processing | Leadership </subtitle><entry><title type="html">How to prepare for the MS in Human Language Technology program</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Prep-for-MSHLT/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to prepare for the MS in Human Language Technology program"/><published>2025-08-28T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-28T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Prep-for-MSHLT</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Prep-for-MSHLT/"><![CDATA[<p>Many students who are interested in the <a href="https://linguistics.arizona.edu/ms-hlt">M.S. in Human Language Technology</a> program at the University of Arizona have a strong interest in language, and many have academic backgrounds that include some kind of formal study of language—but might not include formal coursework in computer science or programming. In order to start our program, however, students are required to have at least a basic proficiency in programming, preferably in Python. Many students who successfully complete our program are able to reach this required level solely through self-study, using the many high-quality, free resources that are available online. <strong>This is the advice that I typically give about this kind of preparation.</strong></p> <p>If you still need to get a foundation in basic Python, there are a number of free options available. One of our faculty has written a book, “<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Python-Linguists-Michael-Hammond/dp/1108737072">Python for Linguists</a>,” which you can use as a self-study reference. You can find an online, self-paced <a href="https://arizona.openclass.ai/classes/python-foundations">Introduction to Python on OpenClass.ai</a>. Alternatively, you can find a more formal (but still free and somewhat self-paced) alternative in Harvard/edX’s <a href="https://www.edx.org/course/cs50s-introduction-to-programming-with-python">Introduction to Programming with Python</a>. (The companion course, <a href="https://www.edx.org/course/introduction-computer-science-harvardx-cs50x">CS50X Introduction to Computer Science</a>, provides a more general introduction covering Python as well as C, HTML, Javascript, and SQL.) Once you have a basic grasp of Python, you could even pursue a slightly more advanced foundation with something like UCSD/edX’s <a href="https://www.edx.org/course/python-for-data-science-2">Python for Data Science</a>. As well as introducing important Python libraries like <a href="https://www.w3schools.com/python/numpy/numpy_intro.asp">NumPy</a>, <a href="https://www.w3schools.com/python/pandas/default.asp">Pandas</a>, and <a href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/">Scikit-Learn</a>, this course introduces tools like <a href="https://jupyter.org/">Jupyter Notebooks</a> that are not technically restricted to Python but are often used in NLP and data science.</p> <p>If, on the other hand, you’re mainly hoping to get better prepared for other courses in NLP, you should know that the textbook for many of our courses, <em>Speech and Language Processing</em>, has a draft version that is available online for free at <a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~jurafsky/slp3/">https://web.stanford.edu/~jurafsky/slp3/</a> . You’re not at all required to read or understand any of this prior to starting our courses, but if you have time, you could work through at least the first few chapters of this textbook to get a better understanding of foundational NLP concepts that we’ll go through in the courses in the first semester of the program.</p> <p>Whatever you end up doing in order to become more comfortable with programming, I encourage you to <em>actually just program</em>, trying to write programs that solve problems you currently face. Actually trying to use Python to solve a problem you’re familiar with will help you become more comfortable with Python. I’d also encourage you to create a free account on <a href="http://github.com/">GitHub.com</a> and begin to use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git</code> and GitHub to manage versions and improvements to your code. You can find <a href="https://gist.github.com/luismts/495d982e8c5b1a0ced4a57cf3d93cf60">guidelines for best practices with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git</code> and GitHub here</a>.</p> <p>Once you start writing in Python, I also encourage you to <em>read through a lot of clean, model code</em>. In teaching our two introductory online courses, <a href="/courses/ua_529/">LING 529</a> and <a href="/courses/ua_531/">LING 531</a>, I see many students writing code that will pass the automated tests I provide—so, the code minimally does what it’s supposed to do—but it’s written in a way that is unclear to read, hard to maintain, or requires more processing work than is really needed. For Python specifically, a good source of tips for writing clean code and using Python the best way it can be used is the website <a href="http://realpython.com/">realpython.com</a>. The principles of “Clean Coding” can be found on <a href="http://cleancoder.com/">Uncle Bob’s Clean Coder</a> website and in his books, though they’re not specific to Python.</p> <p>For many of the courses in our program, we recommend setting up your development environment in Linux (such as <a href="https://ubuntu.com/download/desktop">the latest Long-Term Stable version of Ubuntu</a>) or a Linux-like operating system (including macOS). If you’re accustomed to working with a Windows system, you can create a Linux environment in several ways, including creating a virtual machine with <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/">VirtualBox</a> or a similar tool, establishing an Ubuntu cloud desktop with a provider like Amazon Web Services, or adding Ubuntu to your computer in a single-boot or <a href="https://www.mikekasberg.com/blog/2024/05/20/dual-boot-ubuntu-24-04-and-windows-with-encryption.html">dual-boot configuration</a>. Your first HLT course will help you with this process, but becoming familiar with Ubuntu and how to use it prior to the course will help you get up to speed more quickly when that time comes. If you plan to use an Ubuntu virtual machine for your development environment, we recommend that you have a computer with at least 8 Gb of RAM.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="MSHLT"/><category term="HLT,"/><category term="teaching"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Do you want to learn how to use language technologies to create effective tools to support languages and communities? What do you need to know before starting the MS in HLT program?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Language Technologies FOR ALL</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/LT4All/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Language Technologies FOR ALL"/><published>2025-03-05T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-05T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/LT4All</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/LT4All/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eric-m-jackson_imagine-for-a-moment-waking-up-one-morning-activity-7303082319005827073-f0Mm">See this post on LinkedIn</a></p> <p>Imagine for a moment, waking up one morning to discover that your language could not be used on any of your devices. Your phone and tablet do not display your language. None of your devices allow you to type in your language. If you have a smart speaker, it no longer responds to your language. At best, you can record and send an audio message in your communications app of choice (whose interface is no longer in your own language), but the automatic transcription feature no longer works for your language. This was the question posed by one of the speakers at <a href="https://www.lt4all2025.eu/">the UNESCO Language Technologies for All Conference</a> that I attended last week. Sit with this for a moment and reflect on what that would feel like.</p> <p>Although digital devices work just fine for a few hundred of the world’s most populous languages, the situation this speaker asked us to imagine is the daily experience for more than a billion people, who speak one of the thousands of languages for which digital tools—even “simple” tools like keyboards, dictionaries, and spell checkers, not to mention more complex tools like large language models or automated speech recognition systems—do not yet exist.</p> <p>To be sure, for many of these people, digital devices and even access to the Internet are likely unavailable, as well. However, <strong>if our goal is to bring the positive benefits of digital platforms and communication tools to all people, then making those tools function in the languages that those people prefer is an important part of that task.</strong></p> <p>This is a complex problem. One part of the solution involves assembling corpora of digital data in these languages. This is not an easy task, and it raises questions like, <em>who should have the right to manage this kind of language data?</em> Some language communities have taken intentional action to change the trajectory of their language’s digital footprint. At this conference, the <a href="https://naijavoices.com/">NaijaVoices</a> project introduced their concept of “data farming” (an intentional contrast with “data mining”) for languages of Nigeria as an example of a community-based solution to this problem.</p> <p>The trajectory of a language’s digital footprint is also related to issues of language preservation and revitalization. At this conference, we also heard examples of the successful work that has been done by the <a href="https://estonianworld.com/technology/estonias-ai-gamble-can-four-billion-words-secure-its-languages-future/">Estonian</a> and <a href="https://www.prospect-journal.org/articles/blog-post-title-two-yjhc2-rftfm-7lsm8">Icelandic</a> language communities, to develop language technologies that aim to promote the use of these languages in digital contexts.</p> <p>There remains much work to be done, but I’m excited to be among those who are working for equitable approaches that promote the well-being of communities, regardless of the languages that they prefer to use!</p> <div style="position:absolute; width:100%; height:100%;"> <a href="https://www.lt4all2025.eu/" target="_blank"><img src="/assets/img/20250305-1.jpg" style="vertical-align:middle; text-align:center"/> </a> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AILT"/><category term="LinkedIn"/><category term="HLT"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What if you woke up one morning, and your language could not be used on any of your devices?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Celebrating International Mother Language Day</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/International_Mother_Language_Day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Celebrating International Mother Language Day"/><published>2025-02-18T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-18T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/International_Mother_Language_Day</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/International_Mother_Language_Day/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eric-m-jackson_international-mother-language-day-united-activity-7297682735412690944-GNj5">See this post on LinkedIn</a></p> <p>This February 21st marks the 25th anniversary of the establishment of <a href="https://www.un.org/en/observances/mother-language-day">International Mother Language Day</a>. This is a good time to be reminded of what this celebration represents.</p> <p><a href="https://docs.un.org/en/A/RES/61/266">The original UN resolution</a> establishing International Mother Language Day highlights several points about language:</p> <ul> <li><strong>multilingualism</strong>—when one person speaks more than one language—is a means of promoting, protecting and preserving diversity of languages and cultures globally</li> <li>genuine multilingualism promotes unity in diversity and promotes international understanding, both of which contribute to peaceful and mutually beneficial international relationships</li> </ul> <p>Since this is a UN resolution, it’s natural that it focuses on issues at an international scale. However, issues of language and multilingualism can be found at any level of society, from the international scale, to your town, and to your own neighborhood and schools. There are people in the places where you shop, the places where you or your children study, or even the places where you worship, who speak languages that are different from yours. That should not represent a barrier to be overcome, but an opportunity for you to learn from a different way to look at the world.</p> <p>Next week, I’ll be attending <a href="https://www.lt4all2025.eu/">the UNESCO Language Technologies for All Conference</a>. Even though multilingualism can “[foster] social development by promoting inclusion, preserving cultural heritage, and empowering language communities,” language communities differ in the language technologies that are available to them, and this results in differences in how easy it is for communities to reach their goals for their members. As part of the <a href="https://ailt.arizona.edu">Advancing Indigenous Language Technologies working group</a>, I’d like to see access to appropriate language technology tools grow for <em>all</em> of the roughly 7000 languages in the world today, not just the 50 or 100 that happen to have the most data online.</p> <p>Is there something that you could do to celebrate International Mother Language Day this year? Consider starting by simply finding out about the other languages that are spoken where you live. Tucson is the traditional home to communities who speak Hiaki and O’odham, and many other languages can now be found around town. Taking the next step and trying to <strong>learn</strong> one of these languages, to paraphrase Humphrey Bogart, could be the beginning of some beautiful friendships.</p> <div style="position:absolute; width:100%; height:100%;"> <a href="https://www.un.org/en/observances/mother-language-day" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.un.org/sites/un2.un.org/files/2020/01/mother-language-poster.jpg" style="vertical-align:middle; text-align:center"/> </a> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AILT"/><category term="LinkedIn"/><category term="HLT"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There's value in celebrating all languages]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Maintaining our values</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Keep_to_our_values/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Maintaining our values"/><published>2025-02-12T09:16:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-12T09:16:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Keep_to_our_values</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Keep_to_our_values/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eric-m-jackson_dei-nsa-dei-activity-7295475385578704896-OwTL">See this post on LinkedIn</a></p> <p>We need to make sure that the current push to get rid of DEI in government is not simply a stealthy way to reintroduce bias, echo chambers, and other things that will hinder us. Whether the recent infamous photo of a wall being repainted at the FBI academy was really at the FBI academy or not <a href="https://www.snopes.com/news/2025/02/07/fbi-core-values-mural/">https://www.snopes.com/news/2025/02/07/fbi-core-values-mural/</a>, we need to maintain the values that we hold as a country, regardless of the winds of administrative change. Those values include diversity, equity, and inclusion, as well as compassion, fairness, integrity, respect, and stability.</p> <p>Dr. Renée Burton makes the case well in this post.</p> <blockquote> <p>“Being insecure about common sense words like: diversity. equity. inclusion. will destroy not aid our economy.”</p> </blockquote> <iframe src="https://www.linkedin.com/embed/feed/update/urn:li:share:7291958128059854849" height="1598" width="504" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" title="Embedded post"> </iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="LinkedIn"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Let's maintain the values that have served us well]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MSHLT Student Laura Montenegro</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Laura_Montenegro/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MSHLT Student Laura Montenegro"/><published>2025-01-27T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-27T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Laura_Montenegro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Laura_Montenegro/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://example.com">See this post on LinkedIn</a></p> <p>Our <em>Master’s in Human Language Technology</em> program had one other student graduate in the fall semester: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/laura-montenegro-872930b2/">Laura Montenegro</a>. For her internship with <a href="https://www.cobaltspeech.com/">Cobalt Speech</a>, Laura evaluated a hybrid ASR model (using a Hidden Markov Model-Deep Neural Network) for <a href="https://medium.com/neuralspace/low-resource-language-what-does-it-mean-d067ec85dea5">low-resource languages</a> using Cobalt’s existing tools.</p> <blockquote> <p>Although “low-resource language” is the standard term to refer to languages without large existing datasets, I find the term “data-scarce language” to be less prone to misunderstanding; the “resource” that is low is <em>prepared datasets</em>, not necessarily money or people.</p> </blockquote> <p>By definition, it’s hard to find datasets for languages that are considered “low-resource,” but Laura found a workable amount of audio data for the Ewe language <a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/worldboss/ewe_bible_v2_tts">on HuggingFace</a>—great practical experience for future work in NLP and speech technology!</p> <p>Wishing you all the best in your future endeavors, Laura!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/20250127-1.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/20250127-1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="MSHLT"/><category term="students"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing MSHLT student Laura Montenegro]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MSHLT Student Charlie Accurso</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Charlie_Accurso/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MSHLT Student Charlie Accurso"/><published>2025-01-17T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-17T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Charlie_Accurso</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Charlie_Accurso/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eric-m-jackson_although-most-of-the-students-in-our-%F0%9D%98%94%F0%9D%98%A2-activity-7286053758436851712-Fiy4?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop">See this post on LinkedIn</a></p> <p>Although most of the students in our <em>Master’s in Human Language Technology</em> program graduate in the spring semester, there are a few who graduate in the fall. One of those who completed the program just a few weeks ago is <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/charlieaccurso/">Charlie Accurso</a>. For his internship, Charlie worked as a Language and AI Engineering intern on call center software, using skills in multiple languages. Because his work will be applied by his host company in an actual project, we can’t publicly share more than this!</p> <p>It’s one goal of our program that practical experience like this prepares students to make significant contributions to their workplace as soon as they finish the program. We wish you all the best in your future endeavors, Charlie!</p> <p>Check out Charlie’s public projects on his GitHub page:</p> <p><a href="https://github.com/charlieaccurso">https://github.com/charlieaccurso</a></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/20250117-1.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/20250117-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="MSHLT"/><category term="students"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing MSHLT student Charlie Accurso]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MSHLT Student Ashwin Raj</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Ashwin_Raj/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MSHLT Student Ashwin Raj"/><published>2025-01-06T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-06T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Ashwin_Raj</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2025/Ashwin_Raj/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eric-m-jackson_with-each-new-academic-year-its-inspiring-activity-7282082146414931969-M_56?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop">See this post on LinkedIn</a></p> <p>With each new academic year, it’s inspiring to read about the projects that the students in our <em>Master’s in Human Language Technology</em> program pursue for their internship. I recently read through the portfolio for <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ashwin-raj-056140181/">Ashwin Raj</a>, who developed an Invention Classification and Market Research Tool for <a href="https://techlaunch.arizona.edu/">TECH Launch Arizona</a>. It’ll be a fortunate company that hires Ashwin when he completes his degree program this spring. I’m optimistic that he can find a role that aligns with his desire to make a positive impact in the world!</p> <p>Check out this and Ashwin’s other projects on his portfolio site:</p> <p><a href="https://ashwinr136.github.io/HLT-Internship/portfolio.html">https://ashwinr136.github.io/HLT-Internship/portfolio.html</a></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/20250106-1.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/20250106-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="MSHLT"/><category term="students"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing MSHLT student Ashwin Raj]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Who and What comprise AI Skepticism? | Eric Jackson</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/who-and-what-comprise-ai-skepticism-eric-jackson/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who and What comprise AI Skepticism? | Eric Jackson"/><published>2024-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/who-and-what-comprise-ai-skepticism--eric-jackson</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/who-and-what-comprise-ai-skepticism-eric-jackson/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A re-post of a re-post? Yes, I'm sorry, but I'm going to do it anyway because I found this essay helpful (and found it because of Gary Marcus). I like the way that this essay lays out the different kinds of "AI Skeptics" there are--and I think that these are possibly not mutually-exclusive labels, a fact which I think the author of this post, Benjamin Riley , would agree with. The labels are helpful to summarize some of the nuances of the perspectives on AI that people hold, and although some of the labels denote different nuances, some of them can be held at the same time by the same person. I found it helpful to reflect on where in this taxonomy my own perspective would land. Large language models are doing 𝘴𝘰𝘮𝘦𝘵𝘩𝘪𝘯𝘨, and sometimes that something can be helpful, but if you don't already know enough about the problem you're asking it to solve, it can also lead you astray (as I've had to demonstrate for my freshman formal methods class many times this semester), and it does come with serious 𝘤𝘰𝘴𝘵𝘴. A worthwhile read! Thank you for this take on synthesizing the "AI Skeptics" field, Benjamin!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vector Databases Are the Wrong Abstraction | Eric Jackson</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/vector-databases-are-the-wrong-abstraction-eric-jackson/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vector Databases Are the Wrong Abstraction | Eric Jackson"/><published>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/vector-databases-are-the-wrong-abstraction--eric-jackson</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/vector-databases-are-the-wrong-abstraction-eric-jackson/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This morning, I had just finished preparing a video+code module that introduces Retrieval-Augmented Generation systems to students in my grad-level 𝘐𝘯𝘧𝘰𝘳𝘮𝘢𝘵𝘪𝘰𝘯 𝘙𝘦𝘵𝘳𝘪𝘦𝘷𝘢𝘭 course. Then I saw this post, thanks to a comment by Keegan Reeve. This article includes a lot of helpful observations (and improvements to implementing a database of vector embeddings) for the IR-portion of a RAG system. I hope my students are listening! Thanks, Daniel Ruiz Riquelme for highlighting this post from Timescale!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How language data can benefit your organization | Eric Jackson posted on the topic | LinkedIn</title><link href="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/how-language-data-can-benefit-your-organization-eric-jackson-posted-on-the-topic-linkedin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How language data can benefit your organization | Eric Jackson posted on the topic | LinkedIn"/><published>2024-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/how-language-data-can-benefit-your-organization--eric-jackson-posted-on-the-topic--linkedin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://euangeleo.github.io/blog/2024/how-language-data-can-benefit-your-organization-eric-jackson-posted-on-the-topic-linkedin/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Your data enables insights. Your data drives decision-making. Understanding your data brings benefits, to you and your organization. 𝗪𝗵𝗮𝘁 𝗶𝗳 𝘆𝗼𝘂𝗿 𝗱𝗮𝘁𝗮 𝗶𝗻𝘃𝗼𝗹𝘃𝗲𝘀 𝗵𝘂𝗺𝗮𝗻 𝗹𝗮𝗻𝗴𝘂𝗮𝗴𝗲? What do I mean by data that involves human language? I mean passages of text, short or long; responses to a single question, or technical documents of hundreds of pages. This data might be structured or semi-structured, perhaps in a relational database or in a collection of submissions from a web form. It might be data that is completely unstructured, perhaps in a large collection of text files or PDFs. • 𝗜𝘀 𝗶𝘁 𝘁𝗼𝗼 𝗹𝗮𝗿𝗴𝗲? Are there decisions you need to make based on that data, but you have too much data to analyze easily by having a person look over it? • 𝗜𝘀 𝗶𝘁 𝘁𝗼𝗼 𝗰𝗼𝗺𝗽𝗹𝗲𝘅? Is there information that you need to extract from that data? Do you need to answer questions based on that data? Summarize part or all of that data? Maybe even create a search tool to answer arbitrary questions based on that data? • 𝗔𝗿𝗲 𝘆𝗼𝘂 𝘀𝗵𝗼𝗿𝘁-𝘀𝘁𝗮𝗳𝗳𝗲𝗱? Are you or your organization missing out on benefitting from language data because you or your team lack the skills to work with it? Or maybe you have people with the skills to analyze the data, but they don't have enough time to address something that you see as a strategic problem. Students in our 𝘔𝘢𝘴𝘵𝘦𝘳'𝘴 𝘪𝘯 𝘏𝘶𝘮𝘢𝘯 𝘓𝘢𝘯𝘨𝘶𝘢𝘨𝘦 𝘛𝘦𝘤𝘩𝘯𝘰𝘭𝘰𝘨𝘺 program are trained in programming and NLP skills, and each of them needs to complete a practical project where they apply these skills in a real-world task. 𝗦𝗼𝗹𝘃𝗶𝗻𝗴 𝘆𝗼𝘂𝗿 𝗽𝗿𝗼𝗯𝗹𝗲𝗺 𝗰𝗼𝘂𝗹𝗱 𝗯𝗲 𝘁𝗵𝗲 𝗵𝗶𝗴𝗵𝗹𝗶𝗴𝗵𝘁 𝗼𝗳 𝘁𝗵𝗲𝗶𝗿 𝘀𝘁𝘂𝗱𝘆 𝗽𝗿𝗼𝗴𝗿𝗮𝗺! Got language data? Let's start a conversation. Working with one of our HLT students might bring you the solution you're looking for!]]></summary></entry></feed>